<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="2.4.0">Jekyll</generator>
<link href="http://www.krtierney.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
<link href="http://www.krtierney.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
<updated>2017-03-06T20:22:01+00:00</updated>
<id>http://www.krtierney.com/</id>
<subtitle>Web developer, writer, editor, photographer.
</subtitle>
<entry>
<title>A (Pointed) Guide to Beer</title>
<link href="http://www.krtierney.com/2017/03/06/pointed-guide-to-beer/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A (Pointed) Guide to Beer" />
<published>2017-03-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
<updated>2017-03-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>http://www.krtierney.com/2017/03/06/pointed-guide-to-beer</id>
<content type="html" xml:base="http://www.krtierney.com/2017/03/06/pointed-guide-to-beer/">&lt;p&gt;The slideshow below contains my slides from &lt;a href=&quot;https://skillsmatter.com/skillscasts/9865-london-ruby-lightning-talks&quot;&gt;LRUG’s 13 February lightning talk
meet-up&lt;/a&gt;.
If you missed the meet-up, I’d highly recommend watching some of the talks at
that link—particularly Lola’s talk about finding your dream job, and Paul’s
bizarre journey through balanced ternary. I would not, however, recommend watching
my talk. If you’d like to learn a bit about beer, the outline here will give
you a decent overview and touch on everything included in the talk. If you’d like
to learn about why I hated giving a talk and never want to do it again, well,
there’s &lt;a href=&quot;{{base_url}}/2017/03/05/no-more-talks-please/&quot;&gt;a place for that&lt;/a&gt; too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, beer. I’ve been a beer snob for as long as I can remember. After I moved to
London a couple of years ago, I started working for BrewDog, who are big
proponents of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cicerone.org&quot;&gt;Cicerone certification program&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a Certified Cicerone, I have a greater-than-average depth
of knowledge about beer: serving, storage, brewing,
history, beer styles, pairing with food, off-flavours, et cetera. When faced with
a 10-minute time slot and a staggering breadth of existing knowledge to draw upon,
 I opted to provide a general overview: enough detail that most people might
 learn something new, but a simple enough starting point that I felt reasonably confident
 I wouldn’t lose anyone’s interest right off the bat. So, without further ado, here’s the outline
 of the talk. You can download a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dropbox.com/s/34nvlp481uwcddf/lrug-kt-slides.pdf?dl=1&quot;&gt;PDF of these slides&lt;/a&gt; if you’d like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-pointed-guide-to-beer&quot;&gt;A (Pointed) Guide to Beer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why // When // How&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why drink beer?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brewing is a craft which requires precision, creativity, and attention to detail—
much like coding!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Beer goes well with food. A good food and beer pairing can be a magical experience,
evoking emotional response or feelings of nostalgia. Unexpected pairings can
enable you to perceive flavours you wouldn’t expect to find in both food and beer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It contains alcohol, which lower inhibitions. Some people like that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When to drink beer?&lt;/strong&gt;
This is a trick question. There’s no wrong time to drink beer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How should one drink beer?&lt;/strong&gt;
There are many ways to drink beer, but Ruby is all about a single opinionated approach,
so this is presentation contains strong opinions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Drinking beer at a pub&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It’s important to find the right kind of pub—many taps, or a long,
handwritten list of beers, breweries, and ABVs on a blackboard are good indicators.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you’re in a pub that doesn’t have good beer, my recommendation is to order
a gin &amp;amp; tonic instead. Bad beer is a waste of time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Once you’re in the right place, ask for a taste of something that sounds interesting.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you really don’t know where to start, chat with the bartender for a bit. Bartenders
in good beer bars generally know about beer and can tell you what’s tasting good at the moment.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get a recommendation. If you describe 2-3 beers you know you like, the bartender can probably
recommend something similar for you to try.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Try something new! New beers are released all the time. It’s tempting to get stuck in a rut and
order the same thing every time once you’ve found something you like, but that’s pretty dumb.
Don’t do that. Try new things.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Beer can range in ABV from 0.5% to 40%+ for some ice-distilled varieties, so be careful
and pay attention to the ABV when you’re ordering. Don’t be stupid, remember to drink water
or eat something if you’re drinking a lot of strong beers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t be a dick. This is where I “subtly” pointed out that if your bartender is giving
you a lot of tasters and great recommendations, they’ll be incentivised to continue
providing that kind of service (which they’re not obligated to provide) if you engage in
this practice some parts of the world call “tipping”. Don’t knock it ‘til you’ve tried it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to drink beer, Part 2:&lt;/strong&gt;
Appreciating beer requires a balance of four main senses: Appearance, Aroma, Mouthfeel, and Taste&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appearance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Beer colour is measured in degrees SRM (standard reference measure), ranging from
1 for very light lager to 40+ for black beers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Most beer styles should have perfect clarity, but unfiltered, hazy beers are
becoming rather common among London craft breweries. Some classic styles, like
Hefeweizen, are intentionally cloudy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you see bubbles clustering on the inside of your glass, congratulations, the bar
you’re drinking in has dirty glassware. Bummer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aroma&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Aroma is delivered from the beer to your nose in the little bubbles of carbon dioxide
that pop on the surface.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Swirl the beer in the glass to generate a bit of foamy head, activating aromatic compounds.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Take a few small sniffs, then a deeper inhalation. If you get too acclimated to the aroma
and can’t detect it as well, try sniffing the back of your hand to reset your nose.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Most of the aroma in beer comes from hops added late in the brewing process.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hop aromas vary widely depending on the variety. Some common hop aromas you might
encounter include citrus (lemon, grapefruit, orange), tropical (passionfruit, pineapple), grassy/herbal/floral, pine, mint, marijuana (typically described as “dank”).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mouthfeel&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Take a sip of the (hypothetical) beer, swirl it around in your mouth and over the tongue&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The sensation left in your mouth in referred to as “mouthfeel”. Does it coat your tongue? Dry out your mouth?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;High carbonation/more fizz creates a drier, crisper mouthfeel.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;More sugar and heavier body make for a richer mouthfeel.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mouthfeel is one of the most important factors in pairing beer with food.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Taste&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Five elements of beer taste are sweet, sour, salty, bitter, umami.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bitterness is the big one, derived from hops added early in the boil.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sweetness generally comes from malted barley.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Salt flavour can come from minerals in the brewing water or can be added for certain styles.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Umami is generally not a great flavour to find in beer; it can indicate autolysed yeast.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sour beers are my favourite! Sourness can come from the yeast strain or from
added bacteria.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There’s an important difference between &lt;em&gt;good sour&lt;/em&gt;(deliberate) and bad sourness,
such as from infected beer or dirty draught lines.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to buy beer for a poker night&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Buy from local shops and local breweries: Kew, Beavertown, Kernel are all great options.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lower ABV beers are usually more cost-effective.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Classic styles like lager, pale ale, IPA are safe bets and go well with snacks.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It’s more important to have &lt;em&gt;enough&lt;/em&gt; beer than to have expensive beer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be nice to your guests: Provide appropriate glassware if the beer is unfiltered; no
one likes a mouth full of yeast.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Check the dates to make sure your beers are fresh! IPAs and pale ales are best within
six months of bottling (the younger the better). Hop aroma fades quickly and very
old hops can take on a cheesy smell that most people find deeply unpleasant.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If your friends don’t appreciate good beer, save some money and buy crappy beer for them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Yes, they will probably just drink your good beer anyway. If that happens, save the
bad beers and use them to make beer bread or micheladas.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It can be distracting to fuss over fancy beer, so don’t get anything too special if the
purpose of your gathering is to play poker or watch sports.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to pair beer with food if you’re going to dinner at your boss’s house or something&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pairing beer with food is really tough if you don’t know the menu in advance.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The best option is to just buy Belgian beer, since it goes well with food.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Belgian yeast strains have fruity, spicy, peppery notes that bring out
complementary flavours in food.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Saison is a particularly good option—goes well with cheese, meats, vegetables.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They tend to be pretty strong, so if you want something lower ABV, keep an eye out
for “table saison”, also known as grisette.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Beer for dessert?&lt;/strong&gt;
Sadly saison doesn’t go very well with chocolate. Pick out a nice imperial stout or
barleywine to go with dessert.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
<summary>The slideshow below contains my slides from LRUG’s 13 February lightning talkmeet-up.If you missed the meet-up, I’d highly recommend watching some of the talks atthat link—particularly Lola’s talk about finding your dream job, and Paul’sbizarre journey through balanced ternary. I would not, however, recommend watchingmy talk. If you’d like to learn a bit about beer, the outline here will giveyou a decent overview and touch on everything included in the talk. If you’d liketo learn about why I hated giving a talk and never want to do it again, well,there’s a place for that too.</summary>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>On the Cult of Giving Talks</title>
<link href="http://www.krtierney.com/2017/03/05/no-more-talks-please/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On the Cult of Giving Talks" />
<published>2017-03-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
<updated>2017-03-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>http://www.krtierney.com/2017/03/05/no-more-talks-please</id>
<content type="html" xml:base="http://www.krtierney.com/2017/03/05/no-more-talks-please/">&lt;p&gt;I recently gave my first—and quite possibly, last—talk at a tech meet-up. While I’m grateful to LRUG for the opportunity to speak, and to the London Ruby community for being a charitable audience, giving a talk wasn’t an experience I enjoyed. I have conflicted feelings about this realisation,
which I’m sharing in case others find themselves in a similar position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the one hand, I’m very early in my tech career and still in what I’ve fondly come to
think of as “The Magpie Phase.” My interest and attention are piqued by each shiny new thing I learn about. It’s a nice change of pace to want to rule something out as a potential area of interest, rather than being distracted by the latest CSS grid or Raspberry Pi when my time would be better
spent on core foundational skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, it feels as though there’s some pressure in the field to give talks, particularly if you’re from an underrepresented group (e.g., if you’re not a cisgender straight white male). The
perceived lack of diverse speakers is frequently trotted out as an excuse when conference organisers fail to put together a diverse lineup of speakers. I’m always happy to see women on stage as speakers, and it feels a bit hypocritical to be unwilling to &lt;em&gt;be&lt;/em&gt; one of those women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m good at speaking extemporaneously, enjoy crafting a narrative, and have a lot of collected random bits of knowledge about various interesting topics. On paper, I should be an excellent candidate for giving talks. The talk I gave was about &lt;em&gt;beer&lt;/em&gt;, a subject about which I can speak at length without any preparation (or even any prompting, if I happen to have a beer in my hand). It’s not a technical topic, so the imposter syndrome that dogs me on a daily basis doesn’t really come into play. I’ve had to dig pretty deep to try to unpack why I hated being up on stage, but I think I’ve finally hit on it: It all comes back to karaoke.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A large majority of my friends &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt; karaoke. They get together on a regular basis at their favourite karaoke bars. They practice their songs, trying out new material or polishing up old stand-bys. They &lt;em&gt;put on a show&lt;/em&gt;, entertaining the audience, the other singers, and themselves. And as far as I can tell, they do this because they just really love it. They love the attention, they love performing, they love entertaining.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This aspect of giving talks—the part that relies on showmanship, being able to capture and hold an audience’s attention—is the part that makes me feel like my whole body is being dunked in boiling oil or eaten alive by tropical ants. I don’t mind being the centre of attention for a specific purpose, but being on a stage with the expectation of entertaining people, well, that’s never been my M.O. &lt;em&gt;I despise karaoke.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that if I were to give a second talk at some point, I’ve learned a few things and would do a better job. It’s possible I would have enjoyed this more if I were speaking on a technical topic. I almost certainly would have felt more comfortable if I’d arrived early and tested my speaking volume with the microphone. I should have brought my own laptop, so I could have run my slides in presentation mode, with my notes visible on a screen for me but hidden for the audience. As it was, I presented without notes, which would have been fine were the timing not quite so tight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what I really want to know is: Must I? Is there any compelling reason I should put myself through this experience again? Ultimately, I’m perfectly happy to leave the entertaining to people who love the limelight… and that realisation is probably the most valuable lesson I can take from this experience.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
<summary>I recently gave my first—and quite possibly, last—talk at a tech meet-up. While I’m grateful to LRUG for the opportunity to speak, and to the London Ruby community for being a charitable audience, giving a talk wasn’t an experience I enjoyed. I have conflicted feelings about this realisation,which I’m sharing in case others find themselves in a similar position.</summary>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Welcome to Jekyll!</title>
<link href="http://www.krtierney.com/2017/02/25/welcome-to-jekyll/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to Jekyll!" />
<published>2017-02-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
<updated>2017-02-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>http://www.krtierney.com/2017/02/25/welcome-to-jekyll</id>
<content type="html" xml:base="http://www.krtierney.com/2017/02/25/welcome-to-jekyll/">&lt;p&gt;I started out following the quick-start guide on &lt;a href=&quot;jekyll-docs&quot;&gt;Jekyll docs&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;{% highlight bash %}
$ gem install jekyll
$ jekyll new
$ jekyll serve
{% endhighlight %}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I read further through the docs and admired my new creation,
I quickly realised I was going to be making a lot of changes to
the default set-up, even for the simple site I had in mind. After
copying over the layout files from the &lt;code&gt;minima&lt;/code&gt; gem to my site
folder, I set about pruning code, poking around, and
observing how everything is put together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m still learning! Parts of it feel familiar. Jekyll uses
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Shopify/liquid&quot;&gt;Liquid syntax&lt;/a&gt;, which feels familiar after
using Django at my last job. It’s far more powerful than
I need for a site this simple, but it’s fun to have a sandbox
to play around in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I’ve only just realised that Liquid is part of
the Shopify family. I don’t have much experience with
Shopify; all I know of them is that they provide the platform
for most of the revenue to America’s fascist media outlet… so now
I feel much less great about how I spent my Saturday afternoon. 😕&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
<summary>I started out following the quick-start guide on Jekyll docs:</summary>
</entry>
</feed>
